there are a few sites in nature as dramatic as a big cat battling its prey
but cheetahs aren't born ready to hunt
it's a skill their mothers teach them over many challenging months
what does it take to turn tiny cubs into predators to find out
one filmmaker forged an extraordinary bond with a wild cheetah family
and over a year and a half recorded their lives in remarkably intimate detail
thanks to his unique relationship
we can witness cheetah family life extremely close up
and reveal the heartbreak and triumph a cheetah mother faces
as she battles to raise the next generation
on malanga game reserve in zimbabwe
a female cheetah has been keeping a secret
she is the mother of five new cubs
this is a dangerous place for such small ones
so she's been hiding them in thick undergrowth
but her secret is about to be discovered
conservationist and cameraman
kim wala has spent his entire adult life filming africa's wild animals
he had been following the female gaining her trust until she disappeared six months earlier
had a call on the radio
that there was a cheetah with small cubs
and i thought maybe a two
and lo and behold
it was same mother cheetah
and she had five new little cubs
and they were tiny
they were probably just nearly three months old
like all cheetah mothers
she has no partner or sisters to help her feed and protect these vulnerable cubs
that responsibility is hers alone
and she's just over a year to teach them how to survive in the wilderness
without her
but the question for kim was would she allow him back into her world
and it must have been within the first week
i think i got out and i was filming
and the cubs came right up to me
and the mother just lay over there
she wasn't even looking
and that was how the whole thing started
and it was wonderful
the mother's incredible acceptance of kim
would allow him to witness the lives of a wild cheetah family
in a way he never imagined
it wasn't long
and i was walking with them
sleeping with them
and even following them on the hunt
it's spring
and for a single mother
it's no easy task herding five small cats
but her cubs know her by her call over the coming months
they will pay attention when they hear her voice
it's a language we can't understand
but for them
her meaning is always clear
her home spreads for two hundred square miles
between these forested hills and a seasonal river to the west
while this wooded terrain doesn't seem like typical cheetah habitat
she's already successfully raised four cubs beneath this canopy
ho ho ho ho ho
but this doesn't mean that her role as a single parent is easy
the forest harbours many enemies like leopards and lions
even baboons are too powerful for the lightweight mother to stand up to
their fluffy coats help to disguise them in the undergrowth
but when they're on the move
they need to stay close by her side
right now
with five hungry cubs depending on her milk
she must seize every chance to feed herself
her prey the impala
that thrive in these woodlands
every other day she must wrestle one of these powerful antelope to the death
but first she must lose five little shadows
when those cubs were really small
it was quite interesting how she would sneak off hunting
and the little guys would just know if they had to go and hide in
that sort of hide away in a little bush and wait there
her hyperactive cubs can't be trusted to keep still
their play could attract unwelcome attention
but their mother simply can't be in two places at once
she can reach a top speed of nearly sixty miles an hour
twice as fast as an olympic sprinter
but the forest is a hazardous obstacle course for a high speed hunter
as well as her prey
dinner's ready
and she calls her family to join her
but what does she want
their bellies are full with her rich milk
and they're not too eager to share her strange meal
in those early days
when she would take them to a carcass
and they said
look at this thing
and they'd be terrified
what is this thing
what what are we supposed to do with this thing
and then they come
and they started playing with it
and they weren't even bothering to eat
they were just biting and pulling and stuff
it's been a hard day
and she still needs to get a long line of cubs
bath
grooming keeps them clean
but it's also the cheetah version of a hug
strengthening their bond
and then
she still has energy for a bedtime game
that requires unlimited patience from one of the players
but she can never totally let her guard down
the hours of darkness are perilous for these diurnal cats
and tonight the mother can't protect her family from their deadliest enemy
kim had only been filming them for a few short weeks when tragedy struck
the next morning
when i came back
one of the cubs was missing
i searched around
and not far from where i found them
they were lion tracks
i can only presume they killed the cub
but normally lions don't
they don't eat them
so they just kill it and leave it there
and i searched and searched the area for ages
trying to find something
but i never could find anything
the mother has no choice
she has to share her range with larger predators that readily kill competitors
to survive in this forest
she must keep moving her family as far away from the pride as possible
four cubs follow her today
they're all females
except for one
and he soon captured kim's attention
i started developing a relationship with the little male
and i call him solo
what happens when cheetah reach adulthood
the males will go off together
and the females will go and have their own cubs
solo was the only male
so he was going to go off on his own
and it was going to be solo
and my little journey together
by late spring
the hot
dry season has reached its peak and soaring temperatures make the family thirsty
thank you
the only water remains in a shrinking dam where hundreds of birds flock to drink
african waters are treacherous places to take a young family
they can't linger here
there's no cover for cubs
and they're still too small to outrun danger
but she won't need to rely on the dam for much longer
because the summer wet season is about to begin
rain is a whole new experience for the cubs
and within a few short weeks
the only world they've known looks very different
the dry riverbed becomes a stream
then a river cutting off the western edge of the mother's territory
and in secluded corners of the forest
hidden from the family's view
the cubs'first summer will be a season of discovery
aroused by rain from its dry
seasoned burrow
this one's a little withdrawn
his sisters soon lose interest
but solo always inquisitive
is determined to play
now if only he could figure out which end is front
it's been four months since her cubs were born
and the mother's milk is no longer enough to sustain their growing appetites
they need to eat meat
and today they're going to find out just what she has to do to feed them
the forest provides a choice of lookouts to help her locate food
her cubs love imitating her
and an impromptu lesson in hunting is about to begin
this is going to take a whole lot longer than she thought
their stalking technique will improve with practice
for now
solo is the only one showing any aptitude
as she closes in on her prey
the lesson suddenly becomes more compelling
watching her is the best way to learn how to hunt
a signal from her tells them to keep still for the next few critical seconds
the wait is over
and they're eager to get closer to the action
yeah
right over
they've never seen her do this before
and their murmurs betray their anxiety
the ramp is almost twice her weight
his sharp horns are a lethal weapon
and front row seats have become too close for comfort
she needs to clench her small jaws around his throat
until he suffocates
it seems to be a textbook kill
except down does not always mean out with these powerful opponents
but kim had faith in the skills of his superb huntress
when you see how this mother cheetah would catch a big male impala
and then wrestle with this thing
i mean it was incredible strength and the power that she has to
just to hold on to that thing
and then to bring it down
her kill is a triumph for the family
and the little cats have finally developed a big appetite for meat
even the cold hard rain is not going to chase them from this meal
but tonight by lingering at the carcass
the mother is making a fatal mistake
i left the cheetah in the evening
and they had a fresh kill
and when i got back there the next morning
the killer disappeared
and i found them about half a kilometer away
just the three cubs and my little friend solo was missing
so i searched and searched the area
and i found soda lying at the base of a tree
dead and partially eaten
probably because they were on a killer
leopard had come into the smell or whatever
and surprised them
this journey that i was going to go on with solo
had now just suddenly come to an end
and that whole little bubble just got burst instantly
um hum
predators have killed two of her cubs in the space of a month
this is the fate of many cheetah cubs
and a huge challenge for africa's most threatened big cat
if she's to keep her last three little ones alive
she can't afford any more mistakes
so now we were left with three females
and they were doing really well
two months have passed since solo's death
and the seven
month
old cubs have outgrown the protective cloak of downy fur
on their backs over the weeks they witnessed their mother's hunting prowess
and now every free moment is their chance to play at predator and prey
they're also beginning to make themselves known in the neighborhood
some neighbors are less approachable than others
it's been a successful few weeks for the mother and her daughters
but that's about to change
one summer morning
kim arrived to find the family scattered
the cheetah were everywhere
and i just heard cubs
you know
their little whistle all over the place
i found one of the youngsters
and this cub was obviously in a bad way
then i realised it had a serious injury
and it looked like i think a baboon
it probably bit across the shoulders
you know
baboons and cheetah are a serious problem
and baboons do go for them and chase them
and whenever the mother heard baboons
she would just move away from them
her priority is to gather her family together
but her injured daughter cannot keep up
the cub is traumatized
and to make matters worse
biting ants soon begin to swarm all over her
kim is concerned that the ants will eat her alive
until now he has simply been a witness documenting the family's fortunes
he faced a dilemma
should he help the cub or not
we sort of have a policy that if it's a manmade injury
then you come in and you try and sort the animal out
but if it's a natural injury
then you don't
unless it's an endangered species
and in this case we called a vein
he came and helped
we stitched up the cheetah
and then we took her back to her mother
kim's intervention saved her life and brought him even closer to the family
so she would have that scar for the rest of her life now
and then that day i decided to name her
and i named her shennui
i just like that name
the name of a maani tree in the local shangan language
and i just liked the sound of the name
and it suited her
in no time at all little shatze is on the mend
although
it will take a few days before she's well enough to run around with her sisters
but the mother's trials are not over
yet there's more upheaval to come
just days later
one of the other cubs appears thin and unsteady on her feet
within hours she's collapsed and is bleeding from her nose
she has contracted a mysterious and deadly illness
and the mother is helpless
she can offer only comfort nothing more
the disease has taken hold so quickly that even kim is unable to help
her calls urge her daughter to get up and follow her
by nightfall her little one is dead
despite her best efforts
the mother has lost three cubs in seven months
as far as providing goes she could provide
and that was that was never a problem
she was a really good hunter
and she could provide food
but she couldn't protect them from all that other stuff
and that's stuff which a lot of cheetah can't do now
only two cubs follow where once there were five
it will take all her skill
and a huge dose of luck to get her surviving daughters through to adulthood
soon kim began to notice that the two cubs had very different personalities
you know
shannazi was always more calculating and quite independent
while the other cub which i named chini
she was more of a baby and real mommy's girl
she just loved her mommy
and she was really obliging
and later when i needed to track them
she'd let me just walk up to her and put on a radio collar
weeks pass and the rainy season draws to a close
it's difficult to find suitable prey in late summer's long grass
the family spots an impala herd on the far shore
the river's gone down since the rains ended
but they still need to find a shallow place to cross
and these cats don't like to get their paws wet
true to their characters
shanae makes her way across with finesse chini
on the other hand
would rather stay on dry land
and she wants to be sure her mother's coming along
there's no turning back now
the lush summer grazing has left the herds in peak physical condition
the mother must get close
she can't sustain top speed for very long
it's an exhausting struggle
but today
for the first time
her daughters are eager to help her
they might have enthusiasm and instinct
but at eight months old they still lack skill
and it's not clear exactly what chinsu's contribution is
they've participated in their first big hunt
and shatze is eager to claim the trophy
but kim knew what was coming next
cheetah have this funny thing
that youngsters
especially once they've caught this thing
and once it's down on the ground
then that's okay
it's dead now
so we can let go
and then they surprise what day it's got up again
everyone will go hungry today
by autumn
their forest changes colour
and the moani trees that gave shanazi her name start to lose their leaves
change blows in on the cool winds
one morning
two strangers arrive
it's a coalition of brothers with only one thing on their mind
to mate with the mother
unlike other big cats
cheetahs do not typically kill cubs that don't belong to them all
the same chini seems frightened
the mother's aggressive response should leave them
in no doubt that she's not ready to mate
but they're not taking no for an answer
they follow the family deeper into the forest
china's persistent cries are not helping the situation
the brothers aren't giving up
they're after a scent
that will let them know that she's come back into oestrus
and when that happens
she will abandon her cubs to begin a new family
it's as if tindley knows this and objects
their advances are premature
but they'll be back
months pass and the chilly start of winter marks the sister's first birthday
they're growing in confidence
and now approach hunting practice with determination
a bush piglet has been hidden in the grass while its mother is away
foraging
catching such small prey should be a walk in the park
but their mother is still providing for them
and they seem to think this ferocious little snack is not worth the effort
for the moment
elephant dung is a much more compliant prey
they'll sometimes see a piece of dung over there
and they'll go tearing after it
and then grab it and hit it
and then another one will come in from the side
and it's not a game of soccer to them
they love playing those sort of games
and then they'll stand this piece of elephant dung in their mouth
and looking really stupid
and hello
it didn't run away
by late winter
the forest has turned bare and cold
it's over a year since kim began filming
the mother and her five tiny cubs
and now her daughters are nearly the same size as her
but they still depend on her guidance and wisdom
especially when it comes to their arch enemy
this morning they've wandered into a pair of lions
members of the same pride that killed her cub
in their cheetahs sacrifice strength for speed
and now their only defence against these powerful cats is to flee
chini and her mother are ready to run
but shanna's sudden bravado could cost her her life
she's no match for a male lion four times her weight
the mother has already lost one cub to lions
she'll do what she can to save another
and she sees to it that they quickly retreat
shanati needs to be much smarter next time
if she's to survive alongside these deadly enemies
as the months fly by time is running out for the sisters to perfect their hunting skills
today they've managed to catch a rebok
a secretive forest antelope
this adult might be small enough to wrestle
but their technique still needs considerable practice
it's a small victory for the sisters and not their last
over the coming months
the demands on their mother to feed them will lessen
until one day she will know that the time has come
nearly a year and a half has passed since chennai and chinzi were born
and although their mother's made mistakes along the way
she's done everything in her power to get these two survivors this far
now a fresh instinct is beginning to take hold of her
she's preparing for another journey into motherhood and leaves her scent
where it will lure passing males
her daughters might not realise it yet
but this simple action marks the end of their childhood
everything will be different from this day onwards
by some mysterious communication
her cubs know that this time they cannot follow
these strong
healthy cheetahs are a product of her labor and devotion
but are they ready for a life on their own
kim had been anticipating this bittersweet moment for months
well
i knew from the start that one day the mother would just up and and leave them
and the family would begin to dissolve
and i i suppose i was prepared for it
but their mother's abrupt departure hits chini hard
she was so distraught
that mom having disappeared
and she called and called for a couple of days
now chennazi was just very different
when mum was gone
she didn't seem to be too fazed
and it was almost like well now
i'm going to be a normal cheetah
i don't have to run after my mummy anymore
the sisters only have each other now
and the next few critical weeks will either make or break them
as they begin to patrol their forest as adults
a daunting reality soon confronts them
if they're to survive
they'll have to apply their mother's hunting lessons
first climb a tree
scan the area for suitable prey
too tall
way too big
kim had been an intimate witness to the milestones in their lives almost from the start
but the ultimate test of their mother's success was still to come
and i'd seen them catch small prey
but one day they'd have to catch adult impala
like their mother
they see an opportunity
it's summer's end
and shorter days have triggered the annual impala rut
throughout the forest
rams are jousting for the right to mate
days of fighting have weakened the contenders
if the sisters hope to succeed today they need to work together
and they seem to have a plan
shinzo sneaks off to lie in ambush
using the forest as cover
shenanzi stalks closer to the ram
aiming to flush it out
all their mother's teaching has culminated in this crucial moment
shatze launches the attack
they've done it
they'd killed their own impala
and once i'd seen that they were successful and looking after themselves
it was just time that the project had come to an end
they were going off on their own
and they weren't going to stay together for long
and i was going to go off and do my thing
in the months that followed
kim no longer spent his days with the sisters
and he began filming a wild dog family
but there was one farewell still to come
i finished working with them and i hadn't seen them for a year
i was going for this walk and i saw this cheat h in the distance
and i start whistling and doesn't even look at me
and eventually i'll get closer and she still doesn't look now
i realize that it's chinsy
so i go and i sit down a couple of metres from her
and she still doesn't look at him
and i'm thinking
come on chick
i haven't seen you for a year
surely you can acknowledge my presence
i mean
we were quite good buddies at once
then
couple of minutes later
she got up and she came to me
and she started licking my face
and that for me is
you know
why i do what i do
because it's so special
it was very special